<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-10-27T12:16:21-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Spring Endurance + Wellness</title><subtitle>Helping athletes find joy through purposeful training.</subtitle><author><name>Michael Curtis</name></author><entry><title type="html">Training Benchmarks</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/training-benchmarks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Training Benchmarks" /><published>2019-10-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/training-benchmarks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/training-benchmarks">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Disclaimer - Data should not be used as a replacement for coach/athlete intuition. Rather the goal is to capture and report data in a meaningful way so that coach/athlete intuition can be tested and informed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;tl;dr - To create training plans that support a desired, future performance, and in order to measure the ways in which those plans were successful/unsuccessful, coaches and athletes should regularly take metrics on contributors of athlete performance. Also, measuring an athlete’s fitness widely, and not only narrowly (at a single intensity), ensures balanced athletic development across the spectrum. Lastly, performance is key. Whatever improves performance the most is most important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Disclaimer 2 - I’m currently developing an application and personal database for my athletes’ workouts to help inform my coaching decisions. These aren’t the only metrics that are important in creating a training plan, and metrics are only one factor of creating a plan. Further, these are the kinds of metrics that provide insight only after an athlete has been training regularly for some time. &lt;strong&gt;i.e. You shouldn’t use any of the below metrics in a vacuum.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TOC:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#aerobic-threshold-benchmarks&quot;&gt;Aerobic Threshold Benchmarks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#anaerobic-threshold-benchmarks-ex-1-mile-5k-10k-or-10-30-60-minute-tt&quot;&gt;Anaerobic Threshold Benchmarks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#aerobic--anaerobic-power-benchmarks&quot;&gt;Aerobic / Anaerobic Power Benchmarks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;aerobic-threshold-benchmarks&quot;&gt;Aerobic Threshold Benchmarks&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not a secret that easy, steady-state, aerobic training is valuable for all athletes - but how much - and how can you recognize progress - or lack thereof - from everyday gps and heart-rate data. It’s one thing to empiracally say, “I can run further now than I could 6 months ago.” It’s another thing to quantify, “what mixes and types of load produced the greatest aerobic developments during the last 6 months,” and then use that to maximize training adaptations in the future. To answer that question we have to actually track aerobic developments in a meaningful way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I monitor this in two ways: one, I watch for improvements in pace at similar efforts governed by perceived exertion or training in a defined heart-rate zone. and two, I watch for decreases in ratio of pace:heart-rate between the first and second halves of a steady-state session, that is, aerobic decoupling. It’s commonly affirmed that a ratio with 5% or less variance shows a mastery for that particular intensity and distance. That is, the pace you maintain for the second half of your workout only varied in cardio-respiratory cost by 5% or less from the pace you maintained in the first half of your workout. Aerobic-decoupling can be a very valuable metric, but can easily be skewed by temperature, residual fatigue, and elevation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase the pace sustainable for efforts at aerobic intensities.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase the duration or distance of long-runs as decoupling improves (~5% or less).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For Example…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two atheletes go out and run 7.5 miles in 1 hour (8 minutes/mile). Let’s assume they each begin the run at 8:10 minutes/mile, and both climb at the same rate finishing at 7:50 minutes/mile. Fives minutes in, Athlete 1 and 2 each measure a heart-rate of 135. However, 35 minutes into the workout Athlete 1’s heart-rate climbs quickly to 175, while Athlete 2 stays mostly constant, finishing at 140.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Athlete&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Pace1 (min/mi)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Pace2 (min/mi)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;AvgHr1&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;AvgHr2&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Decoupling &lt;br /&gt;(Pace1/Hr1 - Pace2/Hr2) / (Pace1/Hr1)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8:05&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7:55&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;145&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;172&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;17%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8:05&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7:55&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;136&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;138&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.5%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though both the above athletes ran for the exact same time and distance, they got very different workouts. Athlete 1 is likely to be very fatigued after this effort, given the second half of the workout had a 17% higher cardio-respiratory cost than the first half. Athlete 2 probably felt no noticeable change in effort during this run and would likely rate it very easy - easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Athlete&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Outcomes&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;- Might not want to increase the duration of the run until decoupling improves &lt;br /&gt;- Should not attempt this workout volume regularly, but rather use it as a long run&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;- Could easily use this effort as maintenance or even recovery &lt;br /&gt;- Should consider an increase in pace for greater aerobic development during workouts of 1 hour&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;anaerobic-threshold-benchmarks-ex-1-mile-5k-10k-or-10-30-60-minute-tt&quot;&gt;Anaerobic Threshold Benchmarks (Ex. 1 Mile, 5k, 10k or 10, 30, 60 minute TT)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tracking average pace for like distance or duration at near-to-above Anaerobic Threshold can help measure your aerobic endurance &lt;em&gt;(your ability to sustain power over time)&lt;/em&gt; and aerobic power &lt;em&gt;(your ability to produce power aerobically regardless of time)&lt;/em&gt;. Your actual results are a combination of your aerobic and anaerobic abilities, but sessions of at least 10 minutes for untrainined individuals or 30 minutes for trained individuals help minimize the amount of anaerobic input. I prefer to look at this metric as a function of pace rather than completion time, because the confidence of average pace can be validated by correlating it with the range of minimum and maximum pace over the session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase the duration or distance of sessions as mastery of shorter sessions develop.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase the average pace for sessions of like distance/duration, but…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minimize the range between minumum and maximum pace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For Example…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a 30 minute time-trial where one athlete begins at 6 minutes/mile and steadily declines in pace to 8 minutes/mile throughout the session. He averages 7 minutes/mile (4.29 miles). A second athlete begins a 30 minute time-trial, she begins at 7:10 minutes/mile and steadily pushes herself to 6:50 minutes/mile at the end of the session. She averages 7 minutes/mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Athlete&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Duration&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Average Pace&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;(Min - Max) Pace&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30 minutes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7 minutes/mile&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2 minutes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30 minutes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7 minutes/mile&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20 seconds&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second athlete shows more self awareness in pacing (which is a desireable skill to develop), and we also have more confidence that her average pace for the duration accurately reflects her current aerobic endurance. The first athlete showed less self awareness and likely had a greater anaerobic influence, which quickly depleted, making it more uncertain that his average 7 minutes/mile reflects an intensity that he can sustain for 30 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Athlete&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Outcomes&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;- Should continue to work on his self-regulation and body awareness &lt;br /&gt;- Might focus on developing aerobic power to decrease reliance on anaerobic power&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;- Might increase the duration or distance of threshold sessions if it fits her goals &lt;br /&gt;- Should increase the intensity of threshold sessions to accomodate her adaptations&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;aerobic--anaerobic-power-benchmarks&quot;&gt;Aerobic / Anaerobic Power Benchmarks&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benchmarking Aerobic and Anaerobic Power &lt;em&gt;(your ability to produce power)&lt;/em&gt; is best accomplished by measuring the distance completed of time-based repetitions or the average pace of distance-based repetitions. By decreasing the recovery interval between repetitions to 1:1 or less, your body’s ability to rely on anaerobic systems for energy decline and more reliance from aerobic systems occur. To target anaerobic energy systems, a greater repetition:recovery-interval ratio should be used, such as 1:5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is not a hard switch. At all intensities the body produces energy aerobically and anaerobically because all muscles function on an aerobic -&amp;gt; anaerobic spectrum. Ex. Type I (Slow) fibers are not completely aerobic, nor do they all have the same ratio of slow-&amp;gt;fast myosin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase the duration or distance of repetitions as long as intensity &amp;gt; race pace can be maintained.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase the average distance completed during time-based repetitions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decrease the average completion time of distance-based repetitions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minimize the range between minumums and maximums (consistency across repetitions).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An increase in the rate of heart-rate recovery during the recovery intervals over like workouts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A decrease in the minimum heart-rate at the end of recovery-intervals over like workouts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For example…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athlete 1 and 2 both perform a 5 repetition x 1 minute workout with 1:1 intervals. Athlete 1 will have inconsistent intervals, where athlete 2 will be more consistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Athlete&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Rep-1&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Rep-2&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Rep-3&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Rep-4&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Rep-5&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Avg Distance&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;(Min-Max) Distance&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;400m&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;300m&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;325m&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;410m&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;270m&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;341m&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;140m&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;335m&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;345m&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;350m&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;340m&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;320m&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;340m&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30m&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athlete 1 shows a lack of self-regulation, and &lt;em&gt;possibly&lt;/em&gt; greater anaerobic ability than athlete 2 based on his high rep-1. Athlete 2 shows a strong competency for self-regulating over 1 minute 1:1 repetitions, and the ability to perform aerobically at this intensity, given the relatively short recoveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Athlete&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Outcomes&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;- Should continue to work on his self-regulation and body awareness &lt;br /&gt;- Might focus on developing aerobic capacity and grow into his high power output&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;- Might considering programming that boosts, in this case, her aerobic power. (or anaerobic if this was closer to 1:5 recovery-intervals)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><author><name>Michael Curtis</name></author><summary type="html">Disclaimer - Data should not be used as a replacement for coach/athlete intuition. Rather the goal is to capture and report data in a meaningful way so that coach/athlete intuition can be tested and informed.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/time-in-zones.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Let’s Talk About Feelings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/lets-talk-about-feelings" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Let's Talk About Feelings" /><published>2019-09-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/lets-talk-about-feelings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/lets-talk-about-feelings">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/lets-talk-about-feelings/header.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;tl;dr - &lt;strong&gt;It is useful to track not only your workout data, but also how you feel during training.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days ago I was on the phone with a client. We were just connecting for a moment to handle some business, not to discuss training, but I was about a 3 minute walk from home and decided to connect on the previous days workout. This particular athlete is EXTREMELY disciplined at providing feedback after every workout (usually overall feeling, rpe, and some general comments), but for this workout no feedback was given and my take from the data was that it didn’t go very well. He agreed, noting that he just “wasn’t feeling it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My gut told me this was a pattern, that over the last few higher intensity sessions he was having trouble shifting gears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been working on building general fitness for a few months, and this last period we’ve started strengthening his endurance base - spending more time at about 95% MLSSv during significant workouts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Michael Curtis</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/posts/lets-talk-about-feelings/header.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Progress Report</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/progress-template" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Progress Report" /><published>2019-09-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/progress-template</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/progress-template">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi Seth! Here’s a look at your progress between &lt;em&gt;9.1.2019 &amp;amp; 9.16.2019&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;purpose-reminder&quot;&gt;Purpose Reminder&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this period was to continue building consistency, and to continue to improve upon your aerobic fitness by increasing your long run and focusing a calm, steady heart rate during your efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;compliance&quot;&gt;Compliance&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;twocol&quot;&gt;
    &lt;h1 id=&quot;section&quot;&gt;102%&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;of Planned Duration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;twocol&quot;&gt;
    &lt;h1 id=&quot;section-1&quot;&gt;97%&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;of Planned Distance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It looks like you got in a little less worked on planned workouts than originally intended. If you need to adjust your scheduled days or weekly hours, please reach out and let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You missed a total of &lt;span class=&quot;red&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; workouts.  Keep up the consistency!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;totals&quot;&gt;Totals&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;twocol&quot;&gt;
    &lt;h1 id=&quot;section-2&quot;&gt;15.6&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hours Ran&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;twocol&quot;&gt;
    &lt;h1 id=&quot;section-3&quot;&gt;37.5&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Miles Ran&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;zonesbreakdown&quot;&gt;ZonesBreakdown&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;threecol&quot;&gt;
    &lt;h1 id=&quot;section-4&quot;&gt;19%&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Zone 1 - Recovery&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;threecol&quot;&gt;
    &lt;h1 id=&quot;section-5&quot;&gt;38%&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Zone 2A - Extensive Endurance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;threecol&quot;&gt;
    &lt;h1 id=&quot;section-6&quot;&gt;22%&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Zone 2B - Intensive Endurance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;threecol&quot;&gt;
    &lt;h1 id=&quot;section-7&quot;&gt;11%&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Zone 3A - MLSS&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;threecol&quot;&gt;
    &lt;h1 id=&quot;section-8&quot;&gt;10%&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Zone 3B - Max Aerobic&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;threecol&quot;&gt;
    &lt;h1 id=&quot;section-9&quot;&gt;0%&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Zone 4 - Speed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;BULK&lt;/strong&gt; of your training should be in Zones 1 &amp;amp; 2. If your distribution seems off, please reach out. We may reconfigure your zones if appropriate, or it may be that you should adjust your pacing for some of your workouts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;purpose-of-the-coming-period&quot;&gt;Purpose of the Coming Period&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this period is…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Michael Curtis</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Boston Bound and Thankful</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/boston-bound-and-thankful" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Boston Bound and Thankful" /><published>2019-09-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/boston-bound-and-thankful</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/boston-bound-and-thankful">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/boston-bound-and-thankful/header.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a runner, I always wonder if I’m prepared for an upcoming race. Are these shoes the right ones? Is my nutrition good? Am I hydrated well or did I hydrate too much? Did I do well for each training session? We do our best to prepare for the race, and we give our best on race day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training for my second marathon (&lt;a href=&quot;https://runsignup.com/Race/Results/60979/IndividualResult/QFgd?#U28590987&quot;&gt;first marathon 3:54:12&lt;/a&gt;) was a complete eye opener. It opened my eyes to see that I am capable of so much more. This marathon, the Boston Bound Marathon (John’s Creek, GA), is just the start. In the coming years, I plan to take my running to a whole new level - and inspire others to know they are capable of so much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-road&quot;&gt;The Road&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the road to John’s Creek, I knew something amazing was going to come out of me, but I was nervous too. The longest run I had finished in training was only 16 miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Two weeks before the race, my mother died and my siblings and I were overwhelmed with the shock of a loved one’s death and the logistics of funeral arrangements. A special thank you to everyone who helped us through this ❤️&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One week before the race, I began to feel very unwell. To make it through, I just held onto my faith in God and trusted that my training would carry me through.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The night before the race, I was so excited. I had to force myself to sleep (lights off, phone off, everything off). I had the hotel clerk ring my room to wake me up at 3 am to toe the line by 5:30 am.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;200px&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: auto; margin-right:auto; display: block;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/posts/boston-bound-and-thankful/morning-of.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-race&quot;&gt;The Race&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That morning, I was certain something positive would come of my race. Someone asked if I planned to go sub 3:05, but knowing my training, I instantly replied “no”. My only two goals were to run sub 3:30 and to cross the finish line going strong - my coach’s race plan had me running 3:25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found another female runner planning a 3:29 marathon, and I started my race barely glancing at my watch, trying to keep pace with her. I started faster than I should have, but for the first 14-15 miles I was the number 1 female, which I never imagined I could do. It was around mile 15 @ 1:45 that my right ankle began to collapse - an ongoing issue that I’m working to overcome. I had to slow down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout my entire run, I never ceased in giving thanks to God. I knew it was by God’s almighty grace, I’d complete the race happily and successfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At mile 16 or 17 this amazing female runner picked up her pace, lapping me at least twice, but I couldn’t help but feel her positive energy as she remained focused and nailed a 3:09 finish. Over the final 2 1/2 miles, I steadily grew faster (crossing the finish at 6:33 min/mile) and grew happy - grateful to God and everyone who made this possible - finishing in 3:27:06. Special thanks to Stephanie, who aided my table during the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;twocol&quot;&gt;
&lt;img height=&quot;200px&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 25%; margin-right:auto; float: left; display: inline;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/posts/boston-bound-and-thankful/result.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;twocol&quot;&gt;
&lt;img height=&quot;200px&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 25%; float:left; display: block;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/posts/boston-bound-and-thankful/stephanie.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-reward&quot;&gt;The Reward&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I am honest, this Marathon wasn’t decided until 3 months or so in advance. I had trained for 40 days with Michael McNeil as my coach when I got the idea. He inspired me to go further in my running dreams and I can not thank God enough for his impact on my running career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally, I was trying to train for a 50-miler on my own and it just became tedious. I didn’t know how to train for it, nor did I know what to expect. But after a few months of disciplined training, I realized I could actually be fast for my 50. I called up my coach and told him my plans. We agreed to look for a Boston Qualifying (BQ) marathon around early Sept to prepare me for the 50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only did I BQ, but training for this race I gained a lot of confidence and learned new skills as a runner. I thank God for all of my friends, family and running family (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/275679196290211/&quot;&gt;Paducah Area Running Crew&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/River2RiverRunners/&quot;&gt;River to River Runners&lt;/a&gt;) for being a part of my run experience. I wouldn’t trade it for anything in the world!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;twocol&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img height=&quot;250px;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/posts/boston-bound-and-thankful/third.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;twocol&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to follow my journey to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ultrasignup.com/register.aspx?did=63479&quot;&gt;Tunnel Hill 50-Miler&lt;/a&gt; and beyond…&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h1 id=&quot;find-me-on-facebook--instagram&quot;&gt;Find me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/jjonuoha&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/jenniferjunerunz/&quot;&gt;Instagram&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/h1&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Jennifer Onuoha</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/posts/boston-bound-and-thankful/header.jpg" /></entry></feed>