<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-09-09T13:26:56-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">spring endurance + wellness</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Boston Bound and Thankful</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/boston-bound-and-thankful" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Boston Bound and Thankful" /><published>2019-09-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/boston-bound-and-thankful</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/boston-bound-and-thankful">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/boston-bound-and-thankful/header.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a runner, I always wonder if I’m prepared for an upcoming race. Are these shoes the right ones? Is my nutrition good? Am I hydrated well or did I hydrate too much? Did I do well for each training session? We do our best to prepare for the race, and we give our best on race day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training for my second marathon (&lt;a href=&quot;https://runsignup.com/Race/Results/60979/IndividualResult/QFgd?#U28590987&quot;&gt;first marathon 3:54:12&lt;/a&gt;) was a complete eye opener. It opened my eyes to see that I am capable of so much more. This marathon, the Boston Bound Marathon (John’s Creek, GA), is just the start. In the coming years, I plan to take my running to a whole new level - and inspire others to know they are capable of so much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-road&quot;&gt;The Road&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the road to John’s Creek, I knew something amazing was going to come out of me, but I was nervous too. The longest run I had finished in training was only 16 miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Two weeks before the race, my mother died and my siblings and I were overwhelmed with the shock of a loved one’s death and the logistics of funeral arrangements. A special thank you to everyone who helped us through this ❤️&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One week before the race, I began to feel very unwell. To make it through, I just held onto my faith in God and trusted that my training would carry me through.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The night before the race, I was so excited. I had to force myself to sleep (lights off, phone off, everything off). I had the hotel clerk ring my room to wake me up at 3 am to toe the line by 5:30 am.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;200px&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: auto; margin-right:auto; display: block;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/posts/boston-bound-and-thankful/morning-of.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-race&quot;&gt;The Race&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That morning, I was certain something positive would come of my race. Someone asked if I planned to go sub 3:05, but knowing my training, I instantly replied “no”. My only two goals were to run sub 3:30 and to cross the finish line going strong - my coach’s race plan had me running 3:25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found another female runner planning a 3:29 marathon, and I started my race barely glancing at my watch, trying to keep pace with her. I started faster than I should have, but for the first 14-15 miles I was the number 1 female, which I never imagined I could do. It was around mile 15 @ 1:45 that my right ankle began to collapse - an ongoing issue that I’m working to overcome. I had to slow down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout my entire run, I never ceased in giving thanks to God. I knew it was by God’s almighty grace, I’d complete the race happily and successfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At mile 16 or 17 this amazing female runner picked up her pace, lapping me at least twice, but I couldn’t help but feel her positive energy as she remained focused and nailed a 3:09 finish. Over the final 2 1/2 miles, I steadily grew faster (crossing the finish at 6:33 min/mile) and grew happy - grateful to God and everyone who made this possible - finishing in 3:27:06. Special thanks to Stephanie, who aided my table during the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;twocol&quot;&gt;
&lt;img height=&quot;200px&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 25%; margin-right:auto; float: left; display: inline;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/posts/boston-bound-and-thankful/result.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;twocol&quot;&gt;
&lt;img height=&quot;200px&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 25%; float:left; display: block;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/posts/boston-bound-and-thankful/stephanie.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-reward&quot;&gt;The Reward&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I am honest, this Marathon wasn’t decided until 3 months or so in advance. I had trained for 40 days with Michael McNeil as my coach when I got the idea. He inspired me to go further in my running dreams and I can not thank God enough for his impact on my running career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally, I was trying to train for a 50-miler on my own and it just became tedious. I didn’t know how to train for it, nor did I know what to expect. But after a few months of disciplined training, I realized I could actually be fast for my 50. I called up my coach and told him my plans. We agreed to look for a Boston Qualifying (BQ) marathon around early Sept to prepare me for the 50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only did I BQ, but training for this race I gained a lot of confidence and learned new skills as a runner. I thank God for all of my friends, family and running family (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/275679196290211/&quot;&gt;Paducah Area Running Crew&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/River2RiverRunners/&quot;&gt;River to River Runners&lt;/a&gt;) for being a part of my run experience. I wouldn’t trade it for anything in the world!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;twocol&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img height=&quot;250px;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/posts/boston-bound-and-thankful/third.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;twocol&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to follow my journey to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ultrasignup.com/register.aspx?did=63479&quot;&gt;Tunnel Hill 50-Miler&lt;/a&gt; and beyond…&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h1 id=&quot;find-me-on-facebook--instagram&quot;&gt;Find me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/jjonuoha&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/jenniferjunerunz/&quot;&gt;Instagram&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/h1&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Jennifer Onuoha</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/posts/boston-bound-and-thankful/header.jpg" /></entry></feed>